Guide to the Walter Freeman and James Watts collection, 1918-1988 MS0803.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- James Watts Papers, 1926-1982; MS0803 Series 2; 12.5 Linear feet (Box 42, Box 33, Box 34, Box 31, Box 32, Box 29, Box 30, Box 27, Box 28, Box 35, Box 43, Box 40, Box 41, Box 38, Box 39, Box 36, Box 37, Box 24, Box 23, Box 26, Box 25)
  The personal papers materials, and includes lecture notes while Watts was a medical student at the University of Virginia, the Harvey Cushing Society, a festschrift to Watts for his 60th birthday, and family estate papers. They are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1926-77.
  The manuscripts are of drafts of papers and publications written by Watts (unless otherwise noted). It is arranged alphabetically and ranges in date from 1934-65.
  The publications are materials for articles authored by Watts (including three bound volumes). Many of the publications were co-authored with Walter Freeman. They are arranged chronologically, and range in date from 1929-67.
  The conferences papers, lectures materials related to conferences Watts attended and papers he presented. The materials are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1937-74.
  The research materials and include a notebook on surgery kept by Watts in the 1930's. The materials are arranged alphabetically and ranges in date from 1933-57.
  The photographs include a photo of Watts at his 50th year class reunion at VMI, Watts in Himmelfarb Library, his trip to Germany in 1954 with the Unitarian Services Committee, Inc., and former interns who appeared in the oil portrait of Watts. They are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1939-82.
  The video and film materials include an oral history interview with Watts conducted in 1988, a transcript of an interview done with Watts in 1979, and a video of Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Mental Illness (1941). The materials are mostly u-matic tape format with some 16 mm film, and range in date from 1941-88.
  The artifacts include medical instruments and a medal given to Dr. Watts at the International Congress of Neurology in Lisbon, Portugal (1953). The materials range in date from ca.1940-64.
  Some materials in this series show patients; in that case, the materials are restricted.
  - Correspondence, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.1
    - General, 1937-1974 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - American Journal of Surgery, 1947 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Ford, Gerald, 1971-1974 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Freeman, Walter concerning lobotomies and children), 1961 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Groff court case, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Lebensohn, Zigmond, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Letters of thanks for Psychosurgery book, 1942-1951 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1948 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Personal various family members, 1907-1928 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Personal, 1931-1939 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Personal, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Personal, 1941-1945 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Personal, 1946-1951 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Personal, 1952-1962 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Personal, 1976-1982 (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence Personal: Chevy Chase Club, 1950 (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence Personal: Ryan, Aurelia, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Personal Watts III, James Winston (Winston), 1974-1975 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence Personal: Watts, Julia, 1939-1951 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence Personal: Watts, Randolph, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence Personal: Watts III, T. Ashby, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence Personal: Wills, Julia, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Personal Papers, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.2
    - Aerial Firepower Demonstration, Eglin Air Force Base, Florida, 10/08/1958 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - Appraisal of books Watts donated to Himmelfarb Library, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Bills and receipts, 1935-1945 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Biographical information, 1943-1977 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - Brochures, certificates, 1953-1977 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Personal Papers: Consultant to Veteran's Administration Hospital, Washington, DC, 1946-1965 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with hospitals regarding internships, 04/1928-05/1928 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Death of Watts' mother, 1952 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Dinner in honor of Dr. W. Jason Mixter, 12/1955 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Directory of medical specialists, listing Freeman and Watts, 1957 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Expenses and receipts for lectures at Albuquerque VA Hospital, 02/1949 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Festschrift for Watts' 60th birthday, 1964 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Financial -Estate of Major S. P. Halsey, 1940 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Financial - Estate of Julia Harrison, 1938-1940 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Financial - Estate of Maude Watson, 1951-1952 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Financial - Estate of Fannie C. Watts, 1952 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Financial - Investment review of James and Julia Watts, 1943 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Financial Real estate sales contract between James and Julia Watts and Anne Todd Eddy, 11/23/1949 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Financial - T. Ashby Watts, will and investment review, 1951 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Financial - Trust agreement for Randolph Watts (son), 1952 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Financial - Will of Julia Watts (wife), 1947 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - GW School of Medicine postgraduate course in psychosurgery, 1949 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, 1958 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, 1959 (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, 1960 (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - Inauguration of Governor Robert Docking, Kansas, 1967 (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - Lecture notes on tuberculosis taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1926 (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - Lecture notes on dermatology and syphilology taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 (Box 24, Folder 24)
    - Lecture notes on internal medicine taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 (Box 24, Folder 25)
    - Lecture notes on obstetrics taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Lecture notes on orthopedics taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Lecture notes on pediatrics taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1926 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Lecture notes on physical diagnosis taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 ca. (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Lecture notes on practice of medicine taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Lecture notes on surgery taken by Watts, University of Virginia [1/2], 1927 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Lecture notes on surgery taken by Watts, University of Virginia [2/2], 1927 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Personal Papers Lecture notes on urology taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1927 ca. (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Lecture notes on ears, nose and throat taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1928 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Lecture notes on psychiatry taken by Watts, University of Virginia, 1928 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Medical pamphlets, 1926-1927 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Medical school drug lists, with Watts' notes, University of Virginia, 1927 ca. (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Medical school handout on pneumonia, 1927 ca. (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Medical school guidelines for taking a patient history, 1927 ca. (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous expense receipts, 1941-1948 (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous notes and prescription book, 1933-1974 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - National Board of Medical Examiners, 1928 (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Neurosurgical Technique, 1940 ca. (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - News Clippings, 1932-1952 (Box 25, Folder 19)
    - Pamphlets from medical school on various subjects, 1911-1924 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlets from medical school on hygiene and public health, 1925-1927 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Phi Beta Kappa membership, 1928 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Piece of silk belonging to J.H.H. (Watts' wife's grandmother [?]), 1860 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Portraits of Watts and Freeman at GWU, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Religion, Presbyterian Church group meeting, 1956 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Report cards of Winston Watts (son), 1945-1952 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - School report on Randolph Watts (son), 01/1952 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - brochure "Doctors at Work: Report on Unitarian Service Committee Medical Mission, Germany,", 1950 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence and clippings, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence and clippings, 1955 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence in German language, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence regarding travel arrangements to Germany, 04/1954-06/1954 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Howard Brooks, 1953 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Dr, A. Earl Walker, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Dr. T. Riechert, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Dr. W. Tnnis, 1954-1955 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with German doctors, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Lothar Kalinowsky, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence with Wilmer Froistad, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - correspondence, Psychological Cinema Register, Penn State University, 04/1954-08/1954 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - expense reports, 1954 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - itinerary for Germany trip, 06/1954-07/1954 (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - Medical Projects Program, agenda and participating members, 09/11/1954 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - notes from trip to Germany, 07/1954 (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - proposed symposium program for trip to Germany, 08/28/1953 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - Statistical data (supplement to 1945-52), 1953 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, Inc. - Symposium on neurosurgery, Freiburg, Germany, 07/05/1954-07/10/1954 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - World War II ration book and selective service card, 1942 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.3
    - Abscess of the Medulla Oblongata, with George D. Weickhardt, 1943 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Abstracts of articles on Psychosurgery, (collected by Tauber), 1948 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Activities and Goals in Cerebral Vascular Disease, 1965 ca. (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Acute Lymphocytic Meningitis, 1936 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Acute Lymphocytic Meningitis, 1937 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Acute Lymphocytic Meningitis, 01/1937 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Anatomy and Physiology of the Frontal Lobe, 1954 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Angiography in Neurosurgery, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Aseptic (Lymphocytic) Meningitis, 1929 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Bilateral Frontal Ganglioglioma with Epilepsia Procursiva, 1936 ca. (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Bladder Dysfunction in Cases of Brain Tumor: A Cystometric Study, with Charles A.W. Uhle, 1934 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Bladder Dysfunction in Lesions of the Spinal Cord, 1935 ca. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Cancer of the Brain: Newer Methods of Diagnosis and Treatment, 1956 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Cancer of the Brain: Newer Methods of Diagnosis and Treatment (for Dr. Blades in American Journal of Surgery), 1956 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Clinical Neurophysiology, with Bernard J. Alpers, 1934 ca. (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - A Comparative Study of the Anterior Cerebral Artery and the Circle of the Willis in Primates [1/2], 1934 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - A Comparative Study of the Anterior Cerebral Artery and the Circle of the Willis in Primates [2/2], 1934 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Cortical Autonomic Epilepsy, with Charles H. Frazier, 1934 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Cystometric Bladder Pressure Determinations in Patients with Brain Tumor: A Preliminary Report, with Charles A.W. Uhle, 1934 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - A Discussion by James Watts of Definitive Diagnosis and Treatment of Headache by Lester Blumenthal, 1957 ca. (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - A Discussion by James Watts of Subdural Hematoma: Analytic Study of 123 Cases by Jose Mateos and Richard Daly, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Effect of Lesions of Hypothalamus on Gastro-Intestinal Tract and Heart in Monkeys [1/4], 1935 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Effect of Lesions of Hypothalamus on Gastro-Intestinal Tract and Heart in Monkeys [2/4], 1935 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Effect of Lesions of Hypothalamus on Gastro-Intestinal Tract and Heart in Monkeys [3/4], 1935 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Effect of Lesions of Hypothalamus on Gastro-Intestinal Tract and Heart in Monkeys [4/4], 1935 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - The Effect of Section of Corpus Callosum on the Motor Performance of Monkeys, 1934 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Effect of Unilateral Lesions of the Lateral Horns of the Spinal Cordon Skin Temperature and Pupillary Size, 1932 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - An Experimental Analysis of the Functions of the Frontal Association Area in Primates, by Carlyle F. Jacobsen, 1935 ca. (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Gliomas in Infancy and Childhood, with Capt. John W. Barrett, 1963 ca. (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - History of the Washington Academy of Neurological Surgery by O. Hugh Fulcher, 1965 ca. (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Influence of Cerebral Cortex on Gastro-Intestinal Movements, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Intususception: of Cerebral Cortex to Intestinal Motility in the Monkey [1/3], 1934 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Intususception: Relation of Cerebral Cortex to Intestinal Motility in the Monkey [2/3], 1934 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Intususception: Relation of Cerebral Cortex to Intestinal Motility in the Monkey [3/3], 1934 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Ligation of the Anterior Cerebral Artery in Macacus Rhesus [Monkeys], 1934 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Lobotomy Manuscripts, 1945 ca. (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Migraine and other Arterial Neuralgias of the Head Relieved by Resection of a Segment of Artery, with Robert H. Groh, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Meningiomas of the Posterior Fossa, with Edward Lang and Ruth Jakoby, 1967 ca. (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Mesencephalic Gliomas [1/2], 1935 ca. (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Mesencephalic Gliomas [2/2], 1935 ca. (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Methods for Pain Relief, 1955 ca. (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Minor Cervical Injuries by K.H. Abbott, et al, 1960 ca. (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Neurosurgical Approach to Chronic Pelvic Pain, 1949 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Neurological Surgery (Courier magazine), 1950 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Neurological Surgery for Relief of Intolerable Pain (abstract), 1958 ca. (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Neurological Surgery in Washington, 1946 ca. (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Notes on cranial fractures and spinal cord (in Spanish), 1955 ca. (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Notes on lobotomy, 1950-1970 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Observations upon the Regulation of Visceral Function by the Brain, 1936 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Pain and Disability [1/2], 1947 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Pain and Disability [2/2], 1947 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Panel on Whiplash, 1955 ca. (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Physiologic Principles in the Management of Head Injuries, 1958 ca. (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - [Prefrontal Lobotomy: Factors Influencing Prognosis], 1946 ca. (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Precision Method Operative Technics (draft), 1948 ca. (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy exhibit, George Washington University, 03/1937 (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in Case of Chronic Polysurgical Addiction, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in Nervous States (presented at George Washington University), 04/16/1938 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Protruded Lumbar Intervertebral Disk by J.P. Murphy, 1950 ca. (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Psychosurgery: A Twenty Year Evaluation (in Spanish), 1955 ca. (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Psychosurgery: A Twenty Year Evaluation, 1956 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Psychosurgery: Retrospects and Prospects Based on Twelve Years' Experience, 1948 ca. (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Psychosurgery: Surgical Aspects, with L. Stanley Durkin (appeared in Progress in Neurology and Psychiatry, 1950) (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Psychosurgery article for book Progress in Neurology and Psychiatry [1/2], 1952 (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - Psychosurgery article for book Progress in Neurology and Psychiatry [2/2], 1952 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Psychosurgery for the Relief of Unbearable Pain, with Walter Freeman, 1946 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Recent Observations on the Diagnosis and Pathological Anatomy of Posterior Fossa Meningiomas, 1967 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - The Relation of Contusion of the Scalp to Post-Traumatic Headache and Dizziness, 1944 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - The Relation of the Frontal Lobes to Visceral Function, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Schizophrenia: Indications for Prefrontal Lobotomy, with Walter Freeman, 1947 ca. (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Significance of Bladder Disturbances in Facial Lesions of the Brain, 1936 ca. (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Significance of Hypotonic Bladder Associated with Colon of the Megacolon Type, 1936 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Significance of Hypotonic and Hypertonic Bladder in Patients with Brain Tumor, 1934 ca. (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Source of Visceral Impulses, with Charles H. Frazier and Charles A.W. Uhle [1/2], 1934 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Source of Visceral Impulses, with Charles H. Frazier and Charles A.W. Uhle [2/2], 1934 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Spinal Epidural Abscess, with correspondence from Ellen Gates Starr, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - "The Spine," a chapter for Surgical Errors and Safeguards written by Dr. Watts, with correspondence with the author Max Thorek, 1955-1957 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - The Surgery of Pain by Herbert Olivecrona, 1946 ca. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Surgical Aspects of Prefrontal Lobotomy (with photographs), 1942 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Traumatic Epilepsy with Cortical Scar, with Stuart N. Rowe (with photographs), 1936 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - The Use of Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Management of the Pain Patient by James Peter Murphy, 06/1949 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Working Ability after Lobotomy, with Arcesio Zuniga, 1951 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Chapters for unknown book: "Intelligence" and "Personality Profile Studies" [Hunt's chapter], undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.4
    - Bound volume: Publications of James Watts, v.1, 1929-1935 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Bound volume: Writings of James W. Watts (1929-1944), v.1 (includes biographical information), 1964 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Bound volume: Writings of James W. Watts (1944-1958), v.2, 1964 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Bound volume: Lobulo Temporal (1964); articles by participants (including Freeman and Watts) in symposium at the National Hospital of Neurology, Mexico City (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - List of publications, 1929-1958 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Aseptic (Lymphocytic) Meningitis, 1929 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Three Cases of Aseptic (Lymphocitic) Meningitis, 1929 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Tuberculous Meningitis with an Unusual Cerebrospinal Fluid: A Case Report, 1929 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Spinal Epidural Granuloma, 1931 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - The Absense of Gonad-Stimulating Hormone in the Urine and Blood of Patients with Pituitary Tumors, 1932 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Zur Pathogenese der Raynaudschen Gangran, 1932 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - The Effect of Post-Brachial Spinal Cord Transection on the Flexor and Extensor Reflexes of the Forelimbs, 1933 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Acute Aseptic Meningitis, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Autonomic Representation in the Cerebral Cortex, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - A Comparative Study of the Anterior Cerebral Artery and the Circle of the Willis in Primates, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - The Effect of Section of Corpus Callosum on the Motor Performance of Monkeys, with Margaret A. Kennard, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Intussusception: The Relation of the Cerebral Cortex to Intestinal Motility in the Monkey, with John F. Fulton, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Ligation of the Anterior Cerebral Artery in Monkeys, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Reciprocal Changes in Reflex Activity of the Fore Limbs Induced by Post-Brachial "Cold Block" of the Spinal Cord, with T.C. Ruch, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 15)
    - The Source of the Impulses Underlying the Effect of Post-Brachial Post Transection on the Spinal Cord upon Forelimb Reflexes, 1934 (Box 34, Folder 16)
    - Influence of the Cerebral Cortex on Gastro-Intestinal Movements (in Symposium on the Functions of the Cerebral Cortex, AMA), 1935 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Mescencephalic Glioma: A Clinical and Pathological Analysis of Ten Cases, with Bernard J. Alpers, 1935 (Box 34, Folder 18)
    - The Relation of the Frontal Lobes to Visceral Function (from the Medical Annals of the District of Columbia), 1935 (Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Abstracts of articles Watts reviewed for Lancet magazine, 1935-1937 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - The Significance of Hypotonic Bladder Associated with Magacolon: Evidence for a Central Origin (from Urologic Cutaneous Review), 1936 (Box 34, Folder 21)
    - Traumatic Epilepsy with Cortical Scar, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 22)
    - The Value of Combining Sedation of the Central and Autonomic Nervous Systems in the Treatment of Epilepsy, 1937 (Box 34, Folder 23)
    - Psychosurgery: Effect on Certain Mental Symptoms of Surgical Interruption of Pathways in the Frontal Lobe, 1938 (Box 34, Folder 24)
    - Acute Lymphocytic Meningitis, 1939 (Box 34, Folder 25)
    - Recent Progress in Neurosurgery, 1939 (Box 34, Folder 26)
    - Intelligence Following Prefrontal Lobotomy in Obsessive Tension States, with Walter Freeman, 1944 (Box 34, Folder 28)
    - The Relation of Contusion of the Scalp to Post-Traumatic Headache and Dizziness, 1944 (Box 34, Folder 29)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Factors Influencing Prognosis, with Walter Freeman, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 31)
    - Psychosurgery for the Relief of Unbearable Pain, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 32)
    - Frontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Unbearable Pain, 1947 (Box 34, Folder 33)
    - Neurological Surgery in Washington, 1947 (Box 34, Folder 34)
    - Development of Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Intolerable Pain, with Walter Freeman, 1948 (Box 34, Folder 35)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Complications and Their Treatment, with Walter Freeman, 1948 (Box 34, Folder 36)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Indications and Results in Schizophrenia, with Walter Freeman, 1948 (Box 34, Folder 37)
    - Psychosurgery, with Walter Freeman, 1952 (Box 34, Folder 38)
    - Journal of the International College of Surgeons, edited by James Watts, 07/1954 (Box 34, Folder 39)
    - Section on Neurosurgery: A New Field of Cooperative Endeavor, 1954 (Box 34, Folder 40)
    - Cancer of the Brain: Newer Methods of Diagnosis and Treatment, 1956 (Box 34, Folder 41)
    - Whiplash Injuries: A Panel Discussion, Watts el al, 07/1957 (Box 34, Folder 42)
    - Malignant Tumors Arising from Peripheral Nerves, with Emmanuele Mannarino, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 43)
    - Guides to the Evaluation of Personal Impairment: The Peripheral Spinal Nerves (Journal of the American Medical Association), 1964 (Box 34, Folder 44)